Guide to the Jane Conlon Muller Oral History Collection AIA.012
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- Michael Flannery (1902-1994), 1991
  - Michael Flannery - 11 December 1991, Dec 11, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Noraid. Founding, purpose, and activities of Noraid. Methods for sending money to Ireland. The organization losing prestige in America in recent times. [10:00 - 20:00] Corruption in the American government and lack of pol
    [15:27] Let's get back to Noraid and some of the things that they did up to the time when you had to go on trial. If you could lead us into that area. How you were accused? What you were accused of?
    [18:17] When who wanted to borrow money?
    [18:29] And you lent them money from Noraid?
    [19:06] How did you do this?
    [19:32] Were arms going over just from this country?
    [20:12] What were you actually accused of that brought about this trial?
    [20:24] When did this trial take place?
    [20:31] And who brought the charges against you?
    [20:44] It was a Federal case then? It was the United States Supreme Court? Against you as an individual or against Noraid?
    [20:56] And who are the individuals that the charges were brought against besides yourself?
    [21:24] And who did you get to represent you?
    [26:07] This all came out in that trial?
    [26:39] Do you recall all of the charges against you?
    [26:59] Frank Durkan represented you or George Harrison?
    [27:11] Who did Paul O'Dwyer represent in this case?
    [27:32] So the charges were sending arms to Ireland? Were there any other charges?
  - Michael Flannery - 11 December 1991, Dec 11, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on Flannery's trial. Perjury of government agents while testifying. Effects of trial on individuals and Noraid. [10:00 - 20:00] Noraid protests outside British consulate and UN during hunger strikes.Raising money for Gaelic Park. Unity of Irish American organizations. Flannery being Grand Marshal of the St. Patrick's Day Parade in 1983. Increased rowdiness of parade crowds. Irish and British governments' opposition to Flannery being Grand Marshal. [20:00 - end] More on St. Patrick's Day Parade. Controversy over Flannery being Grand Marshal.Monument in Nenagh dedicated to patriots who died in revolutionary war. Documentary made about Flannery without his knowledge. Flannery's visit there to unveil a plaque on the monument dedicated to the 10 hunger strikers who died. All the places the documentarians followed Flannery. (Cd 30, Track 1)
    [03:36] Would you tell me the exact date of the beginning of this trial?
    [04:14] Now, you were all acquitted, is that correct? Was there any aftermath or effect that the trial had on you or any of the defendants?
    [04:59] What effect did the trial have on the function of Noraid?
    [06:36] Who brought him down? The United States prosecution did? And then it was the strategy of the defense not to cross-examine him?
    [07:38] What was the general effect, or even specific effect of the supply of arms to Ireland after the trial?
    [08:00] But it did resume later?
    [08:25 ] Who did the crowd consist of?
    [08:51 ] Was it a large courtroom?
    [08:55] Did the trial get a nickname? Were the five of you called anything in particular?
    [09:12] Who do you think tagged that name onto you?
    [09:31] Now that was in 1982. Had you any contact, anything to do with the hunger strikers that had taken place, with their activities that had taken place in 1981. Did you as Noraid or as an individual have anything to do with that?
    [11:01] Was this done mostly through Noraid?
    [11:32 ] Are there any other occasions that you can think of that in the 1980s that brought out large groups of Irish people that you were a part of?
    [12:29] You're saying there was a lot of strength and unity during the hunger strike activities. And then after your trial in 1982 was there any support or any reason? You were still able to in other words able to raise funds.
    [13:02] Tell me something about that [being grand marshal of St. Patrick's Day Parade] ? How were you elected?
    [20:15] Did you almost feel like you were on trial again?
    [20:41] Were you invited for instance to go on any talk shows, radio or tv shows where you actually got paid money during this time? Were you often paid?
    [21:13] Who did the documentary?
    [21:54] Could you please spell for me Nenagh where you said the monument was?
    [22:26] Now this monument, what is it a monument to?
    [23:06] Explain to me what went on when you visited the monument that they documented there.
    [24:44] You mean the ambushes that had taken place many years ago during the Revolution?
    [25:00] Do you play a part in any of these ambushes?
    [25:26] Where did this documentary first appear?
    [25:43] How did you find out about this documentary about you?
    [26:18] How long did it take?
    [26:28] Could you please tell me exactly to the best of your memory, what took place in the documentary footage?
    [28:12] Did you ever find out who these people were that made this documentary?
    [28:33] You mean cable tv?
    [28:44] And you never paid any attention then?
    [28:48] And obviously no one ever thought to give you a copy of this?
    [29:06] Did you find the documentary complementary?
    [29:36] Did you find it factual?
    [30:08] What do you think was the purpose of this documentary?
    [30:25] Did you feel used?
  - Michael Flannery - 11 December 1991, Dec 11, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on documentary.Trips back to Ireland. Reasons for not returning to Ireland until 1949. Involvement with Clan na Gael before the Depression. Reasons for leaving Ireland in 1925. [10:00 - 20:00] Experiences coming to America. More on Clan na Gael and helping unemployed members without family in America. Holding dances to make money.Being declared a foreign agent by the U.S. government. [20:00 - end] More on consequences of being a foreign agent. British propaganda plan against Noraid backfires. Disunity of Irish people during mid 1980s - division in Irish parliament, loss of Gaelic Park, St. Patrick's Day parade, emigration from Ireland - and how it allows Britain to remain in power. (Cd 30, Track 2)
    [00:30] Do you recall the date that this documentary was shown on channel 13? This documentary called, 'The Old Man and the Gun?'
    [02:01] Did anything else ever come from this documentary? Did it affect your life in any other way?
    [03:03] How often do you go to Ireland?
    [03:14] Prior to that you did not go back?
    [04:02] What 64 members were these?
    [04:49] Where was this hall?
    [05:37] What year was this? 1929?
    [05:49] Did you buy from the city?
    [06:11] Rented by somebody else or rented by you?
    [06:17] So that was your speakeasy?
    [07:27] Do you go back yearly?
    [07:35] Do you go back to the same area? Or do you tour Ireland? Or do you visit friends and relatives?
    [08:18] During the Depression, where did you find people who were so needy? Were they members of the Clan na Gael?
    [08:28] They were allowed then to stay in your clubhouse until they got on their feet and got jobs?
    [08:44] So you would say that was the Irish network working in those days?
    [09:01] You made a statement that you planned to go back to Ireland although you thought that you wouldn't be very welcome. Under what circumstances did you leave Ireland?
    [09:52] You did leave voluntarily then?
    [10:27] Did you come by ship under your own name?
    [10:56] There was no ambassador to Ireland at that time?
    [11:07] When was the first ambassador to Ireland, do you recall?
    [14:12] How long did this exist before they all found employment and were well enough to leave?
    [15:04] Did you ever have others join? What kept it at that number [64 members] ?
    [15:17] Then what happened to the Clan na Gael and the clubhouse?
    [15:26] Running the dances still? And where did the profits go?
    [15:47] Until what year were you still in existence there?
    [17:05] Did you own the building at that time or were you still renting?
    [17:21] Were you the president of the Clan na Gael?
    [17:53] What else was going on in your life in 1984, 1985, 1986?
    [19:06] Did the government pay you as a foreign agent?
    [23:59] Did they then cease their propaganda?
    [24:30] So now we're at the middle of the 1980's. Is there anything else that you can think of that you want to share?
    [25:03] You mean the division amongst themselves?
    [27:26] What do you think the main reason is that we're not united?
    [29:20] The reason that they're coming in great numbers again is because there are no jobs in Ireland?
  - Michael Flannery - 14 January 1991, Jan 14, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Continuation of story about first time Flannery captured as member of IRA. Practice of IRA members to give false names when arrested. Charges brought against Flannery. Churches during the Black and Tan War vs. the Civil War. [10:00 - 20:00] More on experiences with IRA and being captured. Description of Mountjoy prison. Building of escape tunnel. Conditions of Flannery's cell in Mountjoy. Story of night of planned escape through the tunnel. [20:00 - end] More on night of planned escape. Attempt to break leaking gas pipe in his cell. Capture of other prisoners in tunnel. Beatings of prisoners who tried to escape. Reasons for being put in solitary confinement. (Cd 31, Track 1)
    [02:25] Where is Mountjoy prison?
    [02:37] When you were first captured, you obviously had to go through an interrogation?
    [03:31] Did you give a false name?
    [04:31] In other words, you would speak to somebody in prison and you would be introduced to him and you wouldn't even know he had a false name, is that what you're saying? That's how quiet everybody was?
    [05:15] I guess you were afraid too that they were spies, was that part of it or not?
    [05:27 ] Did you have certain codes or certain words that you'd use with each other so that you'd know that you were all part of the IRA?
    [06:06] What were you charged with when you were captured?
    [06:51] Were you represented by counsel?
    [07:30] Were the churches a place of safety when you were on the run?
    [09:00] Did the church ever give you a haven when you were on the run?
    [10:13] I guess you didn't get much sleep in those days?
    [10:29] You were interrogated in the first jail, the local jail, then you were brought to another jail you said. Was that a county jail? How did that work?
    [12:06] So it was four feet of stone and dirt?
    [13:24] Did anyone escape through this tunnel?
    [15:40] How long did it take to build the tunnel?
    [15:48] And you found out about it afterward?
    [16:08] Why were you in solitary confinement?
    [18:44] So you had your own clothes in this jail?
    [20:58] This was the same night that the tunnel was going to be finished?
    [22:50] But you stayed in the same cell?
    [25:56] Were you beaten?
    [26:42] How long were you in jail?
    [27:11] Why were you put in solitary confinement?
  - Michael Flannery - 14 January 1991, Jan 14, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] More on experience in prison. Story about being transferred to top tier of women's prison - friendly guard, execution of IRA leaders. [10:00 - 20:00] More on experience in prison.Discussion of Black and Tan War - how it started, establishment of Dail, origination of black and tan name, arrival of British auxiliaries in Ireland. [20:00 - end] More on Black and Tan War - truce, British propaganda, ending.Different fighting strategy during Civil War than Black and Tan War. Flannery's job as a liaison officer and other activities when not fighting during Black and Tan War. (Cd 31, Track 2)
    [08:27] This was the warden of the whole prison?
    [12:35] The Black and Tan War didn't last that long, though, did it?
    [22:31] So how long did the Black and Tan War last, do you recall?
    [23:13] Were you a part of any of this or were you in prison during the Black and Tan War?
    [25:36] When did you do this [work as a liaison officer] ?
    [29:24] So how did you get this position?
    [29:52] Who gave you the assignment?
    [30:06] So you were a volunteer advocate, then, to keep the peace among the community of the Irish, is that correct?
    [31:06] But you would do this all on a volunteer basis?
- Charles J. Hynes (1935 - ), 1991
  The interview with Hynes was recorded in December 1991 at his office in the Municipal Building in downtown Brooklyn. Hynes discusses his childhood, family, and his involvement in Irish American affairs, starting with the 1981 hunger strikes.
  - Charles J. Hynes - 2 December 1991, Dec 2, 1991; [00:00 - 10:00] Kings county district attorney Background - family, childhood, where he developed his Irish identity. How he became involved in Irish American activities - protesting hunger strikes, co-founding Irish Solidarity Day. (Cd 33, Track 1)
    [00:20] May I ask you where were you born?
    [00:26] And your grandparents' names?
    [01:02] Where were your grandparents born?
    [01:17] Even though you didn't have anything to do with your paternal grandparents, they were both born in Ireland?
    [01:34] When did your grandparents come to the United States and if you know, how?
    [01:55] Do you know why they came?
    [02:13 ] Do you know with whom they came?
    [02:35] Do you know what level of education they had?
    [02:45] And do you know how they made a living?
    [03:13] And your grandmother?
    [03:16] How many children did your grandparents have?
    [03:21] And now where was your father born?
    [03:28] Where was your mother born?
    [03:34] What level of education did your father have?
    [03:45] And how did your father make a living?
    [03:51] And your mother?
    [03:54] And how many children?
    [04:01] And where were you born?
    [04:07] And you were raised…?
    [04:12] What is your first recollection of knowing that you were Irish?
    [05:01] Was there any other Irish influence in your life?
    [05:09] Your parents then didn't belong to any Irish American organizations when you were young growing up?
    [05:26] Tell us a little about your military experience.
    [05:44] You said there was no Irish neighborhood experiences growing up?
    [06:01] And what about your religious background?
    [06:10] And you married a woman by the name of…?
    [06:34] And now your children, you have…? And has this Irish influence trickled down to them through the stories that you've told them or Irish involvement that you're in - tell me a little bit about it.
    [07:30] What is the first daughter's name?
    [07:44] Did you ever have a time when you felt you had to defend it [being Irish] growing up? Do you recall when you yourself got active in your Irishness?
    [09:09] What was the focus, merely to protest the hunger strike?
    [09:44] What prompted you to get active and to form this?
    [10:19] Then where did you go from there with your Irish involvement?
    [11:49] Do you think that there's something inside you that draws you to do this that maybe wouldn't be in the being of another political leader that might not be of Irish background, or do you think it's involved with your legal knowledge and professionalism?
    [13:24] Are there other Irish causes that you've been called on to speak out about in recent times?
    [13:52] What about the Joe Doherty situation?
    [14:18] Is there any other Irish-type involvement that you're currently involved in or you just do what comes up when it's necessary?
    [14:33 ] Is there any time in your life or your career where you have felt that someone was prejudiced against you just because you are Irish?
    [15:42] How did you feel?
    [16:38] Do you feel that the Irish have been tagged incorrectly as drunks? What do you think is the reason that they've been so tagged?